Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 800, 2003-2004
    - "A Crash Course in Dubyanomics: President Bush's Economic Policy" No. UK827, 2004 January 6 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 94)
      Robert Barrow, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, Robert C. Waggoner professor of economics, Harvard University, and columnist, Business Week; and Paul Krugman, professor of economics and international affairs, Princeton University, columnist, New York Times, and author, The Great Unravelling: Losing Our Way in the New Century. The decades of the 1980s and 1990s seem to offer two different fiscal models for promoting economic growth. The 1980s under President Reagan suggest that cutting taxes is more important than balancing the budget. The 1990s under President Clinton suggest the importance of balancing the budget with moderate tax increases. Yet the results in each decade were similar: sustained economic growth. President George W. Bush has clearly been following the Reagan model in his first term, enacting large tax cuts even as the federal budget approaches record deficits. But has the Bush team taken the correct lessons from our recent economic past? Do the Bush policies promote long-term growth or jeopardize it?
    - "Give War a Chance? The Utility of War" No. UK828, 2003 November 24 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 94)
      Victor Davis Hanson, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, professor of classics, California State University, Fresno, and author, Ripples of Battle: How the Wars of the Past Still Determine How We Fight, How We Live, and How We Think; and Jonathan Schell, Harold Willens Peace Fellow, Nation Institute, and author, The Unconquerable World: Power, Nonviolence, and the Will of the People. The Prussian military historian Carl von Clausewitz famously observed that "war is merely a continuation of politics by other means." These "other" (violent) means have been used on countless occasions throughout human history to settle conflicts over lands, resources, and political rule. But what is the utility of war in the modern world? In a world with weapons of mass destruction, have the means of war delegitimized its use? In a world of expanding democracy and cultural and economic interdependence, has the use of force become outdated?
    - "A Slave to the System? Thomas Jefferson and Slavery" No. UK829, 2004 January 19 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 95)
      Jack Rakove, Coe professor of history and American studies, professor of political science, Stanford University, and Pulitzer Prize-winning author, Original Meanings: Politics and Ideas in the Making of the Constitution; and Garry Wills, adjunct professor of history, Northwestern University, author, "Negro President": Jefferson and the Slave Power, and Pulitzer-Prize winning author, Lincoln at Gettysburg: The Words that Remade America. When the Constitution of the United States was ratified in 1789, the infamous "three-fifths clause" gave the southern slaveholding states disproportionate power within the federal government. To what extent did this southern advantage help the southerner Thomas Jefferson win the presidency? And to what extent did Jefferson, author of the phrase "all men are created equal," use the power of his presidency to preserve and perpetuate the institution of slavery?
    - "Rock My Worldview: How to Win the War on Terror" No. UK830, 2004 January 19 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 95)
      David Frum, resident fellow, American Enterprise Institute and coauthor, An End to Evil: How to Win the War on Terror; and Ken Jowitt, Pres and Maureen Hotchkis senior fellow, Hoover Institution. Do the neoconservatives know how to win the war on terror? Much has been made of the influence within the George W. Bush administration of neoconservatives--those who tend to take a hard line in the war on terror and who favored the war on Iraq. Recently two men close to the George W. Bush administration, Richard Perle and David Frum, wrote a book laying out the neoconservative agenda for winning the war on terror and making America safe. Their agenda is bold and ambitious. Critics would say it is reckless and dangerous. Who's right?
    - "Another Brick in the Wall: The Separation of Church and State" No. UK831, 2004 January 6 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 95)
      Douglas Kmiec, professor and Caruso Family chair in constitutional law, School of Law, Pepperdine University; and Gary Wills, adjunct professor of history, Northwestern University, Pulitzer Prize-winning author, Lincoln at Gettysburg: The Words That Remade America. The First Amendment of the Constitution declares in part that "Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof." What did this amendment mean to the founders who wrote it? Did they intend to establish an inviolate "wall of separation between church and state?" Or was their intent instead to merely preserve religious freedom and prevent the establishment of a national religion?
    - "A Military Makeover: Transforming the Military" No. UK832, 2003 December 15 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 95)
      Williamson Murray, coauthor, The Iraq War: A Military History; and James Wirtz, professor and chair of the National Security Affairs Department, Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey, California. Despite overwhelming victories by our armed forces in both Afghanistan and Iraq, the United States military establishment is caught up in a major debate on the structure of the military. On one side are traditionalists who emphasize the importance of large ground forces. On the other side are reformers who want our forces to be lighter, smaller, faster, and more high-tech. What are the lessons of the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq? Who is right, the traditionalists or the reformers?
    - "Land of the Setting Sun? The Future of Japan" No. UK833, 2004 January 6 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 96)
      Toshio Nishi, research fellow, Hoover Institution, distinguished guest professor, Reitaku University, Japan; and Steven Vogel, associate professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley. From the 1950s to the 1980s, Japan experienced dramatic economic growth as it transformed itself from a defeated militaristic empire into a democratic high-technology powerhouse. The Japanese economy became so dynamic that, by the late 1980s, some American experts were arguing that Japan would overtake the United States as the world's dominant economic power. And then the Japanese economy collapsed. And for nearly fifteen years, the economic malaise has continued. Why? What does Japan need to do to snap out of its doldrums? And what are the risks and benefits to American interests of a reinvigorated Japan?
    - "Down by Law: Military Detainees in the War on Terror" No. UK834, 2004 February 20 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 96)
      Erwin Chemerinsky, Sydney M. Irmas professor of public interest law, legal ethics and political science, University of Southern California; and John Yoo, professor of law, University of California, Berkeley. Do enemy combatants in the war on terror have any legal rights? The United States now holds more than 650 persons captured during the war on terrorism at our naval base in Guantanamo, Cuba. The government is holding them indefinitely, without charging them and without offering them access to American courts or legal counsel. Is this legal? Do federal courts have jurisdiction in this matter, or do these detainees exist completely outside of the American legal system?
    - "Heaven Can Wait: Is the Pledge of Allegiance Unconstitutional?" No. UK835, 2004 February 20 (Folder VHS, box 19; Digital Betacam, box 96)
      Erwin Chemerinsky, Sydney M. Irmas professor of public interest law, legal ethics and political science, University of Southern California; and Douglas Kmiec, professor and Caruso Family chair in constitutional law, School of Law, Pepperdine University. Is the Pledge of Allegiance unconstitutional? The original pledge, written in 1892 by the Christian socialist Francis Bellamy, did not contain the words "under God." Congress added these two words in 1954. And it is these words that caused the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals to rule in June 2002 that recitation of the Pledge of Allegiance in schools violated the First Amendment's so-called separation of church and state. Now the case is before the Supreme Court. Will the court rule that reciting the current pledge in schools is okay, or do the words "under God" have to go?
    - "Migration Headache: President Bush's Immigration Plans" No. UK836, 2004 March 3 (Folder VHS, box 19; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 96)
      Tamar Jacoby, senior fellow, Manhattan Institute, and editor, Reinventing the Melting Pot: The New Immigrants and What It Means to be American; and Mark Krikorian, executive director, Center for Immigration Studies. It is estimated that currently there are between 7 and 10 million illegal immigrants in this country. Meanwhile the Border Patrol has grown from a staff of 2,000 and a $100 million budget 30 years ago to 11,000 men and women and a $9 billion budget today. Clearly, our attempts to control illegal immigration have not been working. But what should we do instead? President George W. Bush has proposed a new immigration plan that would turn illegal immigrants already here into legal temporary workers. Is his plan an acknowledgment that our economy needs cheap immigrant labor and that we simply can't control our borders any longer? Or is his plan the entirely wrong way to address the immigration problem?
    - "For a Few Dollars More: Global Poverty and the World Bank" No. UK837, 2004 March 3 (Folder VHS, box 19; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 97)
      Douglass North, Bartlett Burnap senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and 1993 Nobel Prize winner in economics, and James Wolfensohn, president, World Bank. Of the 6 billion people on earth, 1 billion--primarily in North America, Europe, and East Asia--receive 80 percent of the global income. Meanwhile 1 billion people subsist on less than one dollar a day. Despite billions in development aid, many Third World nations are no better off than they were half a century ago. Why are developing countries still so poor? And what can international development agencies such as the World Bank do to help?
    - "Iraq of Ages: The United States and the Future of Iraq" No. UK838, 2004 March 26 (Folder VHS, box 19; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 97)
      Donald Emmerson, senior fellow, Stanford Institute for International Studies; Michael McFaul, Peter and Helen Bing senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and associate professor of political science, Stanford University; and Joseph Nye, dean and Sultan Oman professor of international relations, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University. On July 1, the Coalition Provisional Authority--the body headed by U.S. ambassador Paul Bremer that has governed Iraq since the end of the Iraq War--will transfer sovereignty to a temporary Iraqi government. The transfer of power raises a number of hard questions. Will our attempts at nation building in this ethnically and religiously divided country succeed? Just what are our responsibilities in ensuring that success? And how long will or should the United States maintain a military presence in Iraq?
    - "Trading Places: Is Outsourcing Good for America?" No. UK839, 2004 March 26 (Folder VHS, box 19; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 97)
      Stephen Haber, Peter and Helen Bing senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and A. A. and Jeanne Welch Milligan professor in the School of Humanities and Sciences, Stanford University; Kenneth Judd, Paul H. Bauer senior fellow, Hoover Institution; and Harley Shaiken, professor of education and geography, University of California, Berkeley. Does outsourcing--whether it means the transfer of customer service and high-tech jobs to India or of manufacturing jobs to China--benefit the American economy or harm it? And if American workers are being harmed by outsourcing, what should be done about it? Do we need legislation to prevent corporations from sending jobs overseas? Or should we focus our attention on creating new opportunities for the American labor force through education and job training?
  - Series 900, 2004-2005
    - "Red and Blue All Over: The Political Divide in America" No. UK901, 2004 May 3 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 40)
      David Brooks, media fellow, Hoover Institution, and columnist, New York Times; Morris Fiorina, senior fellow, Hoover Institution; and Daron Shaw, associate professor of political science, University of Texas, Austin. During the past decade, neither the Democrats nor the Republicans have been able to capture a majority of the vote in national elections. In fact, the country hasn't been so evenly divided since the 1870s. Some say this is evidence of a culture war and a political divide that has split the country into two Americas. Others disagree, arguing that in fact most Americans are in the moderate middle and are divided on relatively few issues. Who's right?
    - "Around the World in 80 Ways: Affirmative Action around the World" No. UK902, 2004 May 3 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 40)
      Thomas Sowell, Rose and Milton Friedman senior fellow on public policy, Hoover Institution, and author, Affirmative Action around the World: An Empirical Study. In the United States, affirmative action policies, first implemented to address the historical grievances of black Americans, have long been controversial. But the debate over affirmative action has generally ignored such action as practiced by other countries around the world. Has affirmative action proven to be more or less effective in other countries? What common patterns do these programs share? How can the study of these programs help our understanding of affirmative action in America?
    - "Helter Swelter: The Debate over Global Warming" No. UK903, 2004 June 8 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 97)
      Carl Pope, executive director, Sierra Club; and Fred Smith, Jr., president and founder, Competitive Enterprise Institute. This past summer's big-budget disaster movie, The Day after Tomorrow, depicted a near-future in which human-caused global warming dramatically disrupted the earth's climate system, plunging the world in a new ice age. Although the scenario in the film is clearly an unrealistic fantasy, some scientists say that relatively sudden climate change is theoretically possible. But how likely it is depends on whether human activity really causes global warming. Does the evidence suggest that higher amounts of so-called greenhouse gases in the atmosphere due to fossil fuel consumption are, in fact, causing global warming? And if so, what should we do about it?
    - "Mind the Gap: The Racial Gap in Education" No. UK904, 2004 May 3 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 40)
      Bernard Gifford, professor of education, University of California, Berkeley; Abigail Thernstrom, senior fellow, Manhattan Institute, and coauthor, No Excuses: Closing the Racial Gap in Learning; and Stephen Thernstrom, Winthrop professor of history, Harvard University, and coauthor, No Excuses: Closing the Racial Gap in Learning. More than fifty years after the landmark Supreme Court decision Brown v. the Board of Education, there is still an unacceptable gap between the academic achievements of white and black students in America. In fact, by some standards, black students today perform more poorly than they did fifteen years ago. Why? What role does culture play? Does culture explain the disparate performance of Hispanic and Asian students? And just how should we go about trying to close this gap?
    - "The Right Nation: The Conservative Ascendancy" No. UK905, 2004 June 8 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 98)
      Clark Judge, managing director, White House Writers Group and former speechwriter for President Ronald Reagan; and John Micklethwait, U.S. editor, The Economist and coauthor, The Right Nation: Conservative Power in America. A half-century ago, the ideology of the American political establishment was liberal--the New Deal was still new and big government was getting bigger. Today, after a political revolution that began with Barry Goldwater and Ronald Reagan, it may be argued that conservatism has become the dominant ideological force in American politics. But what does conservatism mean today? And if it is ascendant, how long can it remain so?
    - "Is the New Left History? The Past, Present, and Future of the Left" No. UK906, 2004 July 15 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 40; Digital Betacam, box 98)
      Anne Applebaum, columnist, Washington Post and Pulitzer Prize-winning author, Gulag: A History; and Christopher Hitchens, contributor, The Atlantic Monthly and Vanity Fair. In 1960, John F. Kennedy ran to the right of Richard Nixon, arguing that under Republicans, the United States had become too weak in the cold war. A dozen years later, the democratic presidential candidate was George McGovern. How did the Democrats go from hawks to doves in just twelve years? And what does the history of the left imply for John Kerry, the Democratic Party, and the war on terror today?
    - "A Space Case: The Future of NASA" No. UK907, 2004 July 15 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 98)
      Sean O'Keefe, tenth administrator, NASA. In January 2004, President George W. Bush announced a plan for a manned mission to Mars in the first half of the twenty-first century. Is NASA up to the task? Given the recent failures of NASA's manned space program, from Space Shuttle disasters to the over budget and barely functional international Space Station, should NASA even be running a manned space program? If so, what can be done to revitalize NASA and restore both its sense of purpose and the public's excitement for space exploration that has been missing for twenty years?
    - "The Next Great Leap: China and Democracy" No. UK908, 2004 July 15 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 98)
      William McGurn, chief editorial writer, Wall Street Journal; and Orville Schell, dean, Graduate School of Journalism, University of California, Berkeley. It has been more than fifteen years since the People's Liberation Army crushed the pro-democracy rallies in Tiananmen Square in Beijing, killing hundreds of students and workers and wounding thousands more. Since then, although stifling political dissent, China has continued to liberalize its economy and is rapidly becoming an economic superpower. Will the explosion of new wealth in China lead to new pressures for democratic reform? And just what is the legacy of Tiananmen?
    - "Sleeping with the Enemy: The Global AIDS Crisis" No. UK909, 2004 August 26 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 99)
      Carol Adelman, senior fellow, Hudson Institute; and Greg Behrman, author, The Invisible People: How the U.S. Has Slept through the Global AIDS Pandemic, the Greatest Humanitarian Catastrophe of Our Time. The global AIDS pandemic is now in its third decade. Although treatments have improved and infection rates have slowed in the West, AIDS continues to take a staggering toll in Africa. And experts believe that Eurasia, particularly Russia, China, and India, may be next. Is the United States doing enough to combat the global AIDS crisis? Should the United States continue its current policy, which includes an emphasis on getting antiretroviral drugs to millions who can't now afford them? Or does the United States need to focus more on pressuring affected countries to reform their inadequate social and economic institutions?
    - "Unconventional Wisdom: Torture and the War on Terror" No. UK910, 2004 July 28 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41)
      Before September 11, we took it for granted that only nations or states could wage war on the United States. After 9/11 it became obvious that war could also be waged by terrorists operating anonymously and in the shadows. Are the laws of war-the Geneva Conventions, the International Convention on Torture-suited to this new reality of war? Whom may we detain? How may we interrogate those we detain? In the war on terror, do the laws of war permit us to be as tough as we need to be? Peter Robinson speaks with Peter Berkowitz and Jenny Martinez.
    - "What, U.S. Worry? Is the United States Losing Its Competitive Edge?" No. UK911, 2004 July 28 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 99)
      In the last decade and a half, India and China have both engaged in extensive economic reforms, in effect bringing their joint population of some 2.3 billion into the worldwide system of capitalism and free trade. Those 2.3 billion people, many of whom are extremely well educated, are by and large willing to work harder and for less pay than are Americans. Are India and China's expanding and modernizing economies threatening America's long global dominance of science, technology, and industry? If so, what should we do about it? Peter Robinson speaks with Craig Barrett, Stephen Moore, and Peter A. Thiel.
    - "Time Has Come Today: Global Population and Consumption" No. UK912, 2004 July 28 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 99)
      Paul Ehrlich, Bing professor of population studies, Department of Biological Sciences, Stanford University, and coauthor, One with Nineveh: Politics, Consumption, and the Human Future; and Steven Hayward, senior fellow, Pacific Research Institute. In 1990 the United Nations forecast that world population would peak at around 11 billion by the middle of this century. Now many experts believe the peak will be closer to 8 or 9 billion people. Is this slowing of global population growth good news for the earth's environment? Or do we still need to worry about the dangers of overpopulation and overconsumption?
    - "Vive la Difference: Gender Differences and Public Policy" No. UK913, 2004 August 27 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 99)
      Steven Rhoads, professor of politics, University of Virginia and author, Taking Sex Differences Seriously; and Deborah Rhode, Ernest W. McFarland professor of law, Stanford University and author, Speaking of Sex: The Denial of Gender Inequality. When it comes to public policy, is it time to take sex differences seriously? There is no disputing the biological differences between men and women. But how do or should these biological differences influence the roles that men and women play in modern society? Are efforts to create equality in every venue of life--from sports, via programs such as Title IX, to the working world, via the pursuit of subsidized child care and maternity leave--ultimately beneficial for women or harmful?
    - "A Line in the Test Tube: The Debate over Stem Cells" No. UK914, 2004 November 20 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 100)